<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE defcomplib  SYSTEM "http://sources.redhat.com/sid/component.dtd">
<defcomplib lib="libhd44780u.la" dlsym="hd44780u_component_library">
  <defcomponent name="hw-lcd-hd44780u" type="abstract">
    <defpin name="FR" direction="out" legalvalues="binary" behaviors="display"/>
    <defpin name="row-col" direction="out" legalvalues="2 shorts as a 32-bit value" behaviors="display"/>
    <defbus name="bus" addresses="0..1" accesses="byte-wide access"/>
    <defattribute name="refresh-period-msec" category="setting" legalvalues="any positive value" defaultvalue="500" behaviors="configuration"/>
    <defattribute name="verbose?" category="setting" legalvalues="boolean" defaultvalue="false" behaviors="debug"/>
    <variants>
      <defcomponent name="hw-lcd-hd44780u-a00" type="concrete">
      </defcomponent>
      <defcomponent name="hw-lcd-hd44780u-a02" type="concrete">
      </defcomponent>
    </variants>
  </defcomponent>
  <synop>
    <p>
      Simulates the Hitachi HD44780U LCD controller. The controller supports
      1 or 2 lines of 8 5X8 dots with cursor, or 1 line of 8 5X10 dots with cursor.
      The chip includes an 80 character display RAM, a 64 byte character generator
      RAM, and a 240 character ROM of predefined fonts. Two ROMS are available: 
      hw-lcd-hd44780u-a00 specifies the Japanese standard font; hw-lcd-hd44780u-a02
      is the European standard font.</p>
  </synop>
  <func>
    <modelling>
      <p>
	<p>
	  The LCD controller model is somewhat abstracted from the physical device:</p>
	<ul>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      All commands in the model are executed instantaneously, while the real
	      device requires significant time to execute a command. As a result, the
	      busy flag in the model is never set.</p></li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      The real device has 40 segment driver pins, 16 common driver pins, and
	      6 more pins related to data and clock. These are replaced by 2(!) pins
	      in the model. The
	      <pin>FR</pin> (frame) pin is driven to 1 to identify that a new
	      frame is starting, and driven to 0 when the frame is finished. The
	      <pin>row-col</pin> pin incorporates all the functionality of the row and column
	      drivers on the real chip. This pin is driven once for each "on" pixel
	      in the display, and the value on the pin is the [X,Y] co-ordinates of
	      the pixel, encoded as two adjacent 16-bit values in the 32-bit pin value.</p></li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      With these two pins, a display refresh cycle starts when the
	      <pin>FR</pin> pin is
	      asserted; the [X,Y] co-ordinates of all the "on" pixels are then 
	      transmitted on the
	      <pin>row-col</pin> pin; and the FR pin is de-asserted to end 
	      the refresh cycle.</p></li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      The physical device uses an external crystal to set the duty cycle.
	      The model uses the refresh-period-msec attribute to communicate with
	      the scheduler to set the refresh rate.</p></li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      To reduce system overhead, the model tries to reduce its interaction
	      with the scheduler and display. Specifically, a single refresh cycle is 
	      initiated if there is a write to the component, to capture any internal
	      state changes that may affect the display. Because several writes are
	      often required to effect a meaningful change, the refresh is delayed to
	      occur refresh-period-msec milliseconds after the first write. As well,
	      the refresh is continued periodically if blink is enabled.</p></li></ul></p>
    </modelling>
    <behavior name="configuration">
      <p>
	The refresh-period-msec attribute is used specify the refresh period
	(in milliseconds) for continuous update modes such as blink.</p>
    </behavior>
    <behavior name="debug">
      <p>
	The boolean verbose? attribute can be used to track internal operations</p>
    </behavior>
    <behavior name="display">
      <p>
	See discussion of the FR and row-col pins in Modeling section above</p>
    </behavior>
    <convention name="functional" supported="true">
      <p>
	This is a functional component.</p>
    </convention>
    <convention name="Save/restore" supported="true">
      <p>
	Save/restore is supported via the state-snapshot attribute</p>
    </convention>
    <convention name="Triggerpoint" supported="true">
      <p>
	Trigger point support is available on the IR, DR, and AC registers.</p>
    </convention>
  </func>
  <env>
    <p>
      <title>
	Related components</title>
      <p>
	Besides the CPU bus, the LCD controller is typically connected to a
	display of some kind. Clearly, the display component must be aware of the
	refresh protocol used by the HD44780U model. As well, the scheduler is
	typically used to set up the time between refreshes of the display.</p>
      
      <p>
	The following configuration file segment shows how the LCD controller
	can be connected to the lcd.tcl display and host-time scheduler:
      
	<code>      new hw-lcd-hd44780u-a00 lcd	# Standard Japanese font
      new hw-visual-lcd display		# The display is implemented in Tcl
      new sid-sched-host sched		# Use the real-time scheduler
      
      # scheduling (must appear before pin assignments)
      set sched num-clients 1
      set sched 0-regular? 1
      set sched 0-time 500		# in msec

      # display size is in pixels - ie. font-width*display-height
      set display width 40		# 8 chars X 5 pixels per char
      set display height 8		# single line of 8 pixels

      # connect the LCD to the scheduler
      connect-pin sched 0-event -&gt; lcd refresh-sync-event
      connect-pin sched 0-control &lt;- lcd refresh-sync-control
      # connect the LCD to the display
      connect-pin lcd row-col -&gt; display row-col
      connect-pin lcd FR -&gt; display FR</code></p></p>
  </env>
  <refs>
    HD44780U (LCD-II) Dot Matrix Liquid Crystal Display Controller Driver
    (from the Hitachi web site)
  </refs>
</defcomplib>

